Guide to the Roland Herbert Bainton Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Collected Material, Series VII
  - Writings by others
    - Gero, Stephen: "The Byzantine Church and the West: A Survey of Recent Research"; bound with John Rosser: "Recent Research in the History of Byzantine-Western Political and Economic Relations 500-1500 A.D., 1977, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 1080)
    - Hiatt, Ellen H.: "Quakers and Theology as seen through the eyes of Isaac Penington and Lucretia Mott", 1977 (Box 70, Folder 1080)
    - Hiers, Richard:"The Government and Laws of Plymouth Colony, 1620-1660", 1980 (Box 70, Folder 1080)
    - Hitchcock, James: "More and Tyndale on Revelation: The Supremacy of the Book" (Box 70, Folder 1080)
    - Kaegi, Werner: "Ronald Bainton als Darsteller des 16. Jahrhunderts", 1968/69 (Box 70, Folder 1080)
    - King, Margaret Leah: "Thwarted Ambitions: Six Learned Women of the Italian Renaissance", 1975 (Box 70, Folder 1080)
    - Knudsen, Donald: "Young Luther: Comments on Hebrews ", 1981 (Box 70, Folder 1080)
    - Ludolphy, Ingetraut:"Friedrich III. der Weise Kurfurst von Sachsen 1463-1525", 1981 (Box 71, Folder 1081,1082)
    - McConica, James Kelsey: "Erasmus, the Fifth Lateran Council and Church Authority" (Box 71, Folder 1083)
    - MacMullen, Ramsay: "Distrust of the Mind in the Fourth Century" (Box 71, Folder 1083)
    - Murray, John Courtney: "The Declaration of Religious Freedom"(re. Vatican II), n.d. (Box 71, Folder 1083)
    - Muhlenberg, Ekkehard: "Basilides", n.d. (Box 71, Folder 1083)
    - Myers, C.K.:"The Social Attitudes and Teaching of the Churches in America" (Box 71, Folder 1083)
    - Olin, John C.: "Erasmus and the Church Fathers" (Box 71, Folder 1083)
    - Phillips, James M.: "Changing Perspectives in Church History", 1970 (Box 71, Folder 1084)
    - Rabin, Arthur and Lewis Spitz: "The World of Martin Luther", (film script) (Box 72, Folder 1084)
    - Reith, Louis: "The Preceptors of Prince Eberhard of Wurttemberg"; "Refusing the 'Yoke of Slavery': Queen Elizabeth and the Married Estate", 1974,1975. (Box 71, Folder 1085)
    - Russo, François: "Role Respectif du Catholicisme et du Protestantisme dans le Developpement des Sciences aux XVIe XVIIe Siecles", 1956 (Box 71, Folder 1086)
    - Siggins, Ian D.K.: "Luther's Mother Margarethe" (Box 71, Folder 1086)
    - Skotheim, Robert Allen: "Toward the Perpetuation of a Literate and Scientific Culture"; "Humanistic Education in a Technological Age", 1976 (Box 71, Folder 1086)
    - Spalla, Lawrence A.: "How is Roland Bainton's view of Martin Luther and the Reformation shaped by his own background?", 1979 (Box 71, Folder 1086)
    - Thomas, George F.: "Religious Rationalism and Empiricism in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries" (Box 71, Folder 1086)
    - Tracy, James D.: "Luther's Influence on Erasmus' Concept of Faith", 1968 (Box 71, Folder 1086)
    - Urban, Waclaw: "Nova Racoviensia", n.d. (Box 71, Folder 1086)
    - Weber, Erwin: "Cranach and Luther: with selected works of the 'Painting Evangelist' in the United States", 1983 (Box 71, Folder 1086)
  - Material on contemporary social and political issues
    - Miscellaneous (Box 71, Folder 1086)
    - Fellowship of Reconciliation (Box 72, Folder 1087)
    - National Peace Academy Campaign (Box 72, Folder 1088)
    - Promoting Enduring Peace (Box 72, Folder 1089-1092)
    - Promoting Enduring Peace (Box 73, Folder 1093-1096)
    - Collected articles on war/peace/nuclear issues (esp. Vietnam war) (Box 73, Folder 1097-1098)
    - Collected articles on war/peace/nuclear issues (Box 74, Folder 1099-1100)
    - Collected articles on foreign affairs (Box 74, Folder 1101)
    - Collected articles on environment, domestic issues, religion (Box 74, Folder 1102-1103)
    - Collected articles on environment, domestic issues, religion (Box 75, Folder 1104-1107)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series VIII; 7 boxes (3 linear feet)
  - Biographical documentation
    - Biographical statements/ biographical dictionary entries re. RHB (Box 76, Folder 1108)
    - Articles about Bainton -visit to Ikleston, 1919 (Box 76, Folder 1109)
    - Articles about Bainton, 1940s-1978 (Box 76, Folder 1110)
    - Articles about Bainton, 1979-1983 (Box 76, Folder 1111)
    - Articles about Bainton -re. "Where Luther Walked", 1980,1981 (Box 76, Folder 1112)
    - Chronological sequence of biographical documentation: primarily notices of conferences, lectures, travels, etc.; dual (Congregational/Episcopal) ordination debate; incl. correspondence, 1923, n.d.,n.d. (Box 76, Folder 1113)
    - Chronological sequence of biographical documentation: primarily notices of conferences, lectures, travels, etc., 1948-1963 (Box 76, Folder 1114)
    - Chronological sequence of biographical documentation: primarily notices of conferences, lectures, travels, etc., 1967-1976 (Box 76, Folder 1115)
    - Chronological sequence of biographical documentation: primarily notices of conferences, lectures, travels, etc., 1977-1984,n.d. (Box 76, Folder 1116)
    - Notices and correspondence regarding speaking engagements, 1957-1961 (Box 85, Folder 9)
    - Tributes, reminiscences of former students, colleagues -Letters solicited by Gregory Jackson, 1977,1978 (Box 76, Folder 1117)
    - Tributes, reminiscences of former students, colleagues - Sixteenth Century Journal tribute, 1983 (Box 76, Folder 1118)
    - Tributes, reminiscences of former students, colleagues -Reminiscences of former student Ernest Bigelow, 1984 (Box 76, Folder 1118)
  - Memorabilia
    - RHB digest of diary and letters (Box 76, Folder 1119)
    - List of colleagues and their addresses (Box 76, Folder 1120)
    - Address lists, Christmas card lists (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - Bainton family Christmas cards, 1930s (Box 76, Folder 1121)
    - Bainton family Christmas cards, 1942-1971 (Box 76, Folder 1122)
    - Bainton family Christmas cards, 1973-1982 (Box 77, Folder 1123)
    - Honorary doctorate from Earlham College (Box 82, Folder 1168)
    - Emblem from Poland (Box 82, Folder 1168)
    - Obituaries of Bainton and additional memorabilia, 1984, n.d. (Box 84, Folder 10)
  - Family history
    - Genealogical material (Box 77, Folder 1124)
    - Scrapbook of RHB's parents (Box 77, Folder 1125)
    - Charlotte Blackham Bainton's memory book (Box 77, Folder 1126)
    - J. Herbert Bainton -pastorate in Ikleston, England (Box 77, Folder 1127-1129)
    - J. Herbert Bainton -pastorate in Vancouver, Canada (Box 77, Folder 1130)
    - J. Herbert Bainton -pastorate in Colfax, Washington (Box 77, Folder 1131)
    - J. Herbert Bainton -pastorate in Cheshire, Connecticut; incl. corres. (Box 77, Folder 1132)
    - J. Herbert Bainton -writings, sermon notes (Box 78, Folder 1133)
    - J. Herbert Bainton -misc. other documentation (Box 78, Folder 1134,1135)
    - Material re. James Bainton (paternal grandfather of RHB) (Box 78, Folder 1136)
    - Material re. Emily Blackham (stepmother of RHB) (Box 78, Folder 1137)
    - Material re. John Blackham and the Brotherhood Movement (maternal grandfather of RHB) (Box 78, Folder 1138-1144)
    - Material re. Olive Blackham (aunt of RHB) (Box 78, Folder 1145)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits:
      - Roland H. Bainton (Box 78, Folder 1146)
      - Roland H. Bainton (Box 78, Folder 1147)
      - Ruth W. Bainton (Box 79, Folder 1147a)
      - J. Herbert Bainton / Charlotte Blackham Bainton (Box 79, Folder 1148)
      - Children, grandchildren and other relatives of RHB (Box 79, Folder 1149)
      - Older photos, primarily members of Bainton and Blackham families (Box 80, Folder 1150-1154)
      - Miscellaneous individuals, non-family (Box 80, Folder 1155)
    - Group photographs:
      - RHB, his parents and sister (Box 80, Folder 1156)
      - Family (Box 80, Folder 1157,1158)
      - Older photos, primarily of Bainton and Blackham families (Box 80, Folder 1159-1161)
      - Non-family groups including RHB (Box 80, Folder 1162)
      - Non-family groups not including RHB (Box 80, Folder 1163)
    - Buildings/places/things
      - re. Blackham (Box 81, Folder 1164)
      - Ilkeston, Vancouver, Colfax, Cheshire (Box 81, Folder 1165)
      - mostly England (Box 81, Folder 1166)
      - miscellaneous (Box 81, Folder 1167)